hi welcome back to lamrim
and i don't know we're having trouble
waking up
uh happy earth day and those of you who
have
your guinea practice it's also sichu
and among the two kinds of statue it's a
tenth statue
which means the moon is waxing
and that's a nice crescent to bow down
to if you know what i'm talking about
it's the best question to build down
there okay all right
so anyway it's a good day here we go
we're going to start at shay lana me
okay and don't forget where we are
by the way i always start talking fast
in the early morning it's the coffee
uh right so anyway i'll slow down
uh we're in the middle
of tonkapa explaining
chandigarhi explaining
nagarjuna which pablo mache used in his
number
okay especially about who gives birth to
who
right okay so we were talking about
uh the idea of sambara
to wake you up for fifty dollars who can
tell me somebody
it's not sunburned by a way which is
chuckles
oh good yeah some butter to carry very
much
but it's the word for
[Music]
yeah the two collections okay so i don't
know anybody money right
i should pay myself
[Laughter]
yes environment collection but remember
som kappa says look uh
the per can mean
to embrace somebody and maybe that's
what wife really means
huh the embracer uh
so i gotta think about that anyway the
two collections
means the two big piles of
pure good karma that we need to make a
buddha body in a buddha mine
okay and he's talking about
those two collections okay
so when we say two collections what it
really means
is to get it right wisdom and merit
okay to to do them
perfectly and it doesn't mean accumulate
more numbers of good deeds or something
like if you don't get enough good deeds
you don't get your buddha arm
you got one arm it's not like that
okay although it feels like that doesn't
it when you say collection
so he says please remember
that the word sambar collection which is
the
word we use for karma
when we're talking about buddhas or what
creates buddhists
don't forget some compasses embrace
embrace what here's the answer dre
boards in
okay uh
it embraces the final result okay
so if it's a collection if it's really
good karma it will embrace
a buddhist body and mind okay that's all
why are we talking about that well for
one thing
you're gonna be short on your collection
of
something if you don't have bodhichitta
merit yeah okay
all right
[Music]
okay
there's a normal kind of collection of
good karma
if you don't talk about it in terms of
embracing perfection you know normal
people can
pile up karma and we can call it sambar
[Music]
the point is what separates
uh even
self-made bonus from listeners
is that they are better at soaking
collecting okay at collecting all right
now uh he's talking about even in the
desire realm
in their final birth lopanchenki
now he's talking about what is a
self-made buddha right
and you guys know this story what's the
nickname for a self-made buddha
yeah a medium buddha or a half buddha
i'm starting to like half buddha i just
started to
consider that translation
so do becomes a young in their final
rebirth
and they say in the desire room okay
they don't need other teachers okay and
the minute
somebody hears that and i've watched it
for 50 years
everyone says i don't need a teacher i'm
this one
i'm this guy you know i don't need a
teacher i know everything
that's very dangerous sanitary okay
and i've had it so i know about it
but uh you do need a teacher you do need
teachers okay
these are very unusual beings
who can pretty much get to enlightenment
uh by the way consider
this okay it's not that
they got really close in their last life
and then they fell in front of a truck
okay it's not like that
i mean you feel like it should be like
that right it's not like that
it's that in their last life
they finally got the collections good
enough
to create uh nirvana
but they couldn't finish they got the
karma
to to get to nirvana but it didn't go
off
and then they died okay so they're a
person
who has the karma in their heart to
reach nirvana almost immediately
but they died so it's not like
it's not like they collected all this
karma and then
they can work more in this life or
something like that it's not really like
that it's that
they were about to reach nirvana and
something happened
and then in this life there's no choice
they have to reach nirvana that
that karma is called
what's what's what sutra is that
the yoga sutra okay
in their next life
they will not seen in this life seen in
the next life
they will they will reach nirvana got it
okay so they got all this coming
together
and then they died and that's why we say
they don't need a teacher in the next
life it's not that they somehow teach
themselves
it's that the karma's already in motion
and they couldn't avoid it if they
wanted to
you see what i mean it's not that they
are super smart
which is what people think when they
hear they don't need a teacher
it's that they just died accidentally
that they were gonna reach nirvana
anyway okay
so it's not that in this life they're so
smart they don't need a teacher
it's that the karma was already
projected
they just died if they don't do anything
they're still going to reach nirvana in
this life
okay because the karma was strong
okay all right
what's this
it means they reach nirvana
okay when we say they are self-made
buddha they're not a
buddha okay some main buddhists are not
buddhists
did they raise enlightenment they
reached the enlightenment of their trap
and that's why they go around saying
words like total enlightenment which
used to irritate me
what you can get half enlightened you
know what
part of your brain does why do you say
total enlightenment
in fact the sanskrit is samyaksambura
yandapa total
per perfectly total enlightenment isn't
every enlightenment perfectly tell
enlightenment the answer is
no okay
[Music]
yeah therefore when we say by the way
the
the the sanskrit is pratyaga buddha
the tibetan is rang sang yey
but what it means is rang chum se rang
chum
there's a very famous rang chung in
tibetan
50 dollars
[Music]
come on okay cancel the bet
uh if a stone like a boulder
looks like a buddha
we call it rang self
uh like you pick up a leaf and it looks
like
a buddha head or something that's called
rangchu
and it's a special kind of karma you
know
like like when i was uh doing some
deep retreats in a cave i couldn't find
a cave that didn't have snakes and
coyotes in them and tarantulas
and then i saw a big boulder that looked
like my teacher's head
and i said that's that's it you know and
it was getting dark and i
i climb up and i found this cave you
know so that
kind of boulder is called okay why are
we talking about that
these these buddhas are
self-made buddhas okay the sanskrit
is solitary buddha the tibetan is
self buddha and and to encompasses
the self means self made buddha
okay so i don't call themselves buddhist
because you'd be confused
i always translated as self made buddha
and that comes from this sentence
in tonkapa he says self buddha
means self-made buddha and the tibetan
word is rang
and and in other tibetan traditions
the idea of rang chung yeshi
self-made wisdom is very important okay
like uh
what's his name who born in
padmasambhava
okay all right yay here we go
by the way i have a picture power wow
wow
of a lady making a part
yeah i i just feel like she's creating
her and like she's making herself into a
buddha okay i
i think of her as the pop
and it's a nice idea of i just had this
vision of
of a potter making herself into a buddha
it's kind of a nice idea right okay
now uh the original
lines by chandi kirti master chandi
kirti
where he talks about who gave birth to
who
he says the listeners
and the self-made buddhas came from the
but he didn't use the word buddha
yeah nice fifty dollar gmat paid
jimmy 50 that's self-made money
okay and we'll split it afterwards okay
no yeah so muni means buddha and
and the tibetans translate it
as able one tupa capable one
okay like tupten is a common tibetan
name
it means the teachings of the able ones
okay
so muni means capable one what's it mean
in sanskrit really
[Music]
means spiritual silence
to keep spiritual silence which we
didn't keep at all
this retreat
i don't know what happened anyway i
guess it was
the time it was coming out of virus
times and we all want to talk to each
other
so anyway muni means the ancient meaning
is the one who doesn't talk much
and it's it's a famous synonym
for a buddha they don't talk much okay
they don't blabla okay and then
indra means lord of the gods
and it means the one who drops the rain
down okay inda means like
unended means
to drop water and dry is a
doer okay so it's rain rain
rain center rain center
is indra so but it means lord of the
gods
number one god so moon nandra
to in is the name
that chandra kirti gave to the buddhists
in his famous opening lines about
who was born by whom who was born
from whom okay then the listeners and
the self-made buddhists
got born from the
lord of sages right the lord of the able
ones
and then who gave birth to them
and then who gave birth to the
bodhichitta
there's three people it's getting a
complicated
ancestral family here okay
we'll talk about it all right we're
gonna get there
okay uh by the way this is going on too
long
we're going too deep and that means
we're going to have some extra classes
so we're going to offer them as dessert
sometime in the next few months or
something like that
it's up to tim but we won't finish what
we have to finish
so i'm not rushing i like to finish it
thoroughly that's just my way okay
and i think it's the right thing to do
okay you shouldn't rush the dharma
okay so anyway uh
now he wants to talk about oh by the way
what are those opening lines
we gotta say okay say cha-choo
every buddhist book
ever written should start with
children okay means
offering chipper like llama chipper
okay and jer means an offering of praise
so at the beginning of every buddhist
book
it's traditional to bow down to
somebody okay it's traditional
and it's traditional to make somebody
say sambar
a commitment to zomba
to finish the book good okay
so every buddhist book every major
classic
will start especially from ancient india
we'll start
with praising somebody
bowing down to them and promising to
write the book
what's the basis of the promise if you
want to get technical
that they will be able to use this to
reach their goal
good that's part of it yeah it's called
the four
connections right
do you remember yeah every buddhist book
should have four
parts one um
yeah it has a short term goal
in this case to learn middleweight
it has a long-term goal which is to
reach buddhahood it has
useful and important subject matter
and the first three are connected which
is number four okay
if you study the subject matter you
learn emptiness
and that gets you to buddhahood and
that's the fourth requirement of a
buddhist book
the three parts should be connected okay
don't
it's called
so the point is in discussing
who gives birth to who
we are using that part from one of the
most famous books in buddhism
okay we are using the part
where the author bowed down to some holy
being
okay uh don't forget that it's important
okay in discussing who gave birth to who
which is proving one of the benefits of
bodhichitta uh
don't forget we are in the middle of the
praise of
by chandra kunti okay that's where it
comes from and it's important to get to
the next part okay here we go
so in the praise he doesn't say
buddhas give birth to listeners
and happiness and buddhists come from
bodhichitta he doesn't say that
he says the lords
of the munis the lords of the able ones
come from bodhichitta and the lords of
the
sorry they come from bodhisattvas and
the lords of the able ones
give birth to listeners inhabitants he
doesn't call them buddhas
he calls them lords of the able one
which in sanskrit is
munendra okay good all right yay we got
it
uh
[Music]
why do they call them lords he says
what's the lord's what what's the lord's
why lords why don't they just call them
the able ones or the moonees or the
silent ones okay
why do they call them the kings of the
silent ones
they have mastered
the king of teachings so we call them
kings
okay they have mastered the king of all
teachings
so we call them kings okay and
kazakhstan
is
and when these
bodhisattvas and self-made buddhas
and listeners really master buddhism
they also have dominion
over the dharma they become
kings so it's not that they have kings
over some government power
why is buddha a king because they are
kings who
they are the absolute lords over the
dharma
that's all that's why they are king it's
not that they push people around
and tax them except they
they they are the kingdoms of the king
they are the kings of the kingdom of the
dharma teachings
got it okay that's why we call them lord
all right
and those teachings themselves are the
kings
okay all right
we have a picture here this is a very
clever picture
there's a guy
what do you call it juggling light bulbs
gestala you went too far this time
yeah he's a master
he's the lord of the able ones who who
else could
juggle enlightenments how many
enlightenments
three self made bitter listener
yay okay all right here we go
two bond denominators
uh then it's from these
kings of the dharma that the listeners
and the self-made buddhists are born
okay and by the way you can't say it
in english but the verb is different
they use the verb which is reserved
for kings and buddhas which is trumba
say tumba
what's the word for star in tibetan
karma yeah so tunkar jungkar
is the tibetan word for holy being's
birthday
so if you're talking about the highest
teacher in tibet
you could say what's their tunkar okay
cool all right uh tube 1
hey how does this birth go like they go
to the hospital and they go to the
maternity ward and you know how's that
work okay somebody's asking a question
how about turn 2 how does that work
now there's six steps okay
the birth of listeners
and self-made buddhas from
lords of lords of able ones has six
steps okay
somebody asked the question okay
so supposedly it's important that
these listeners and half buddhists god
took their holy birth from
full buddhists kings of and kings of
able ones right how does that work
and so kappa says six steps okay six in
china they go like this
six steps okay six steps here we go
number one uh
the full buddha has to come to your
planet
they have to visit your planet we're
talking about
birth what's the birth process number
one
the full buddha comes to your planet
okay
number two they teach the wheel of life
they teach the 12 links they teach
dependent origination okay
cause and effect ingo okay
that's important for later okay they
come to the planet
and they give that famous teaching on
the 12 links okay
which sugang is translating
vasa bandu's commentary and it will take
15 years or something
it's already sketched out we finished
the whole thing it's ready to go
all right then then what happens
people who are attracted to the listener
system
and people who are attracted to the
self-made
buddhist system come and listen to those
teachings
about dependence okay when you're
emphasizing dependence you are not
emphasizing emptiness
good so somehow these lower
spiritual practitioners are more
attracted to teachings about
cause and effect than about emptiness
they
they have to master that first and then
they master emptiness
which is just means the absence of cause
and effect
okay it's two sides of the same coin
right
okay so they listen
and then what's the famous three stages
of spiritual growth what are the famous
three stages
okay
for zero dollars two
some gum
gum in fact uh ceremony's
monster's name is tusamgomling the real
name
is the spiritual center ling
which means island right for
some gong first you go to the
class and you listen to
okay you listen then some
in your car on the way home to wherever
colorado you're like what the heck did
casual
talk about and you're like daydreaming
about
uh that's really some i don't know about
you but i do my best song in the car
you know you listen to the teaching you
get in the car you drive eight hours
home
and you're just thinking about
everything you know hopefully you don't
get in a car accident
and then when you get home you sit down
in your meditation cushion and you
go okay test some go say to
all buddhist education what do you call
it
pedagogy
it has these three steps this is the
system
to change a person in buddhism this is
this system
to develop a person spiritually
okay what's buddhist curriculum
for how long two thousand five hundred
years it hasn't changed okay
they named the monastery to some gum
okay what what is this place oh this is
where you go to some gum
okay go to class to listen in class
some think about it on your own without
formal meditation
and then do formal meditation and burn
it into your brain
okay and we're gonna do some
fun meditation in the next class today
okay we're gonna take those pictures now
and turn them into an experience okay
that comes next all right
all right so don't forget i said six
things are happening
when we want to have a baby when a
buddha wants to have a baby who's the
baby
listeners and self-made buddhists they
do six steps first they
come to the planet okay second day
teach and mainly the 12 links
and then the students to some gum
they listen they think they meditate
how many we got five right there's gotta
be one more right
they're attracted to the twelve
numbers yeah uh yeah that was
part of the learning dependence yeah
okay and then
uh they it works
okay that's number six okay it works
they reached the goals that they were
attracted to
which were not
interplanetary okay
they just wanted to develop themselves
and they reach it and that's their own
nirvana okay
six steps when they reach their own
nirvana
a self-made buddha has been
born got it yay the sixth one was
they finished the gom of tusan gum
and then they reach their goal so really
it's this idea of
five causal steps leading to a
sixth step which is the result number
six
is the result of the first five that's
an important pattern because the next
topic in the long run retreats
is
the sixth the seven part body to the
instructions where
six causes and one result okay
i'm gonna teach you something in seven
steps
but really step seven is the end of the
process
it's not part of the process okay all
right same thing here
yay and we have a silly
picture which doesn't have much meaning
at all
of six steps okay but you know if you
wanna
you know if you wanna review this whole
teaching
if you wanna check to see
if you really got the whole teaching
we can give you all the pictures and you
should be able to tell me what each one
means
and a picture like this is a little
harder because there's six parts of the
picture okay
but if you wanna if after the program on
sunday
night you want to check and see
how good of a student are you
you can look at all the pictures and if
you can identify them
you you're pretty i i have chosen all
the main ideas
okay then you've got the class you can
say you
you're ready to go to the next rimba of
the lum
then you can say you're ready to go to
the next stage of the path okay
yay next part
you know
then this guy asked a question and and
by the way
the sentence ends in yamna means
you may think to yourself why
okay it's a famous device used by
tonkapa you know he's like anticipating
your questions he builds a question in
your mind
and then he says hey were you wondering
why
and you're like yeah and actually he set
it up
he got he brought your mind to a
question and then he says
hey maybe you're wondering you're like
yeah of course i am you set me up
okay so here's the question okay uh
look many listeners
achieve nirvana in that same
life that they got the teaching on
the troubling dependence you know many
listeners
reached their goal of nirvana
in the same life where they got the
teaching on dependence
but what's he going to say
it's so common for the
the self-made guys to lag behind by one
line it's so common for them to finish
and then they don't get to be a nirvana
until the next life
why some 100 300
why is it more common
for self-made buddhas to lag behind by
one life
what's the sign
what's the evidence that they are often
laggers because
how much 300 yay
it's like i don't know i was studying
this last night i was like
duh duh
now the question makes sense right i'll
say the question again
those of you who lost three hundred
dollars
okay so coppa says maybe you're
wondering
listeners get the teaching on dependent
origination
and they become they reach listener
enlightenment
meaning toronto right on the listener
track
and then these self-made buddha guys
they're always lagging
why because they're self-made buddhists
got it which implies that they did it on
their own in their last life
which means they didn't do it in the
life that they learned how to do it
got it so they're always like i don't
know
retards oops that's probably really bad
karma
okay they're always stuck behind so the
other guy says
why is that you know aren't they better
than listeners
like why are they always one lifetime
behind
do they tend to get hit by trucks more
okay it's a good question when you think
about it you know
why do they always lag behind why do you
think they lag behind
because they recent on their own and
that implies they're lagging behind
they should have wasted in the life that
they got taught i got it
okay
i'm going to
it's wrong to say they were born from
the buddhists
because there was such a tragic delay
how can you say they're born from the
buddhas
if there's a whole lifetime delay they
have to go through a hobarto thing
they got to get squeezed out of their
mother's birth canal again
you know their head has to get flattened
out
you know what why are you saying they
got born from the buddhists they had to
go through another
some sorry birth they had to go through
a very painful birth
again why are you calling them so cool
got it you all right you guys are when
you get this quiet i worry
either you're asleep or you don't
understand all right here we go
they do get teachings on
the wheel of life the 12 links okay
and they do therefore here's an
important connection
because they got teachings on sugang's
wheel of life book necessarily
they had insight into something also
emptiness yeah okay you can't get a good
teaching on
the wheel of life and not start
understanding emptiness okay
so he says look they got great teachings
on
the 12 links and so we can say they
already understood emptiness because the
first stupid link is
not understanding emptiness okay if you
learn that you don't understand
emptiness
you already learn some emptiness got it
okay all right uh okay
you guys okay it's kind of early to do
this right
now tong like lam right what's tong mean
to see to see what's the sanskrit
okay cat
three hundred dollars you ready
there's only two english cognates for
dershta there's only two english words
that i know of there's probably more
that come from
dersta okay one
is the name of a famous mountain range
you're looking for anything that has a
der sound in it
[Music]
okay
we have a mountain range near here where
i did my three-year retreat
which is called the dragoons dragoon
comes from a soldier who wears a red
outfit
that was supposed to suggest a dragon
so dragon and dragoon are the only two
words in english that i know of there's
probably more
that come from the same root as
dirsh durstan okay
and the real root is dirk okay
now why is a dragon called drag
uh evil eye they traditionally had an
evil eye if you looked into a dragon's
eye
you would turn to stone or something
like that so dragon means
evil eye got it
the word dragon comes from dershta to
see
like tongnam it's path of seeing is
called dersta right
why are we talking about that here
uh no sorry this dershta means
seen in this lifetime a karmic result
which is seen in this lifetime is called
dersta dragon okay seen
in this life okay why are we talking
about that we were talking about
the time delay for yeah for happiness
good
their enlightenment is not
us negative right like atheist or
apolitical or apathetic okay
it's not seen in this lifetime it's seen
in the next lifetime
so potentially in the yoga sutra calls
it
not seen yet yeah adarshta
why yeah ananda would mean the unhappy
disciple
so funny everybody says ananda and i'm
like oh
poor guy he's ananda
say ah nanda yeah that means ah means
very happy
okay he's probably on nanda and not
ananda
okay it's a pet peeve of mine
all right here we go get back to the
subject yes
look i admit that uh nirvana
for the self-made guys is not
no it's not it's not seen in this life
okay it's seen in the next way right
it's others
got it you okay now 300 lady
now you can take a visit to the dragoons
today and have a picnic
there's a great hotel uh in
what's it called that that little town
over there the mining town
below tombstone huh
bisbee has a great for 300
you can go to the dragoons at bisbee and
have a nice
lunch okay all right
okay
means to experience name means definite
is a special kind of karma
and it means definite to give you a
result
probably you cannot avoid it even if you
do your four powers or whatever it's
gonna be difficult
to get out it's a karma you cannot get
out of okay
it's a karma you cannot get out of and
it happens to be a durster
right next life so what's the karma you
can't get out
yeah that self guy the self buddha is
going to get to his nirvana
in the next life okay all right
sorry means with certainty
certain to be experienced okay
they won't experience it in this life
but they'll experience in the next life
okay
i have a nice picture i i i like this
one
cat will appreciate it
when you talk about a self-made buddha
you're talking about a tree
which regrows itself after a long period
of time
and so i love the picture the picture is
perfect okay
the tree was there
it got cut and then it
came back okay that's the whole idea of
a self-made buddha
you were a powerful practitioner big
tree
in your last life and then there was a
subtle unavoidable
seed at the center of the trunk which
grew again in the next life got it
cool all right all right
same thing by the way we'll go back to
the easy part don't worry
don't don't turn off your zoom we're
going back to the easy part
sometimes it's nice to stretch your
brain
and by the way if you keep stretching
your bane every day
it's it's incredible what happens to
your brain is nice
it's d but it's it's like doing
a hard yoga every day okay all right
saint dear nyan de ma top gyan maybe
they don't miss nirvana in this life
set up chanting me about kona they were
100 percent sure
to reach nirvana in their next life okay
they did that to some gum three-step
process of buddhist education pedagogy
pedagogy pathological anyway
they got what they wanted okay they by
the way there's a
irony and they got what they wanted
explain
there's an irony in saying they got what
they wanted
yeah all they wanted was nirvana all
they wanted was to take care of
themselves
and it's a tragedy that they got what
they wanted
got it okay all right
stephanie
[Music]
okay and and to say they got what they
wanted
for them is always a two-step
process meaning this life and next life
okay
it it's always delayed until the next
all right cool
danny then uh chad kirti
sorry jetson kappa quotes
uh arya deva who's are you demon
yeah the only thing you can say about
arie davis
oh he was our inaugural student okay
yeah he's the one who gave up his eye
because he was frustrated or then he got
frustrated okay
anyway his most famous book is called
the 400 verses okay
who's nagarjuna's teacher
as you say
a high yogi
the 400 verses
okay
if you understand emptiness
well even if you don't under
reach nirvana in that life you will
without much hard work reach nirvana
in your next life it's like that kind of
karma and he doesn't say what kind of
karma but there's a kind of karma called
certain to be experienced in your next
life okay
so he's quoting
ayadeva to prove that self-made buddhist
can happen
okay all right next picture i think
so i'd i'd like to talk about something
okay we have time
uh another reason to see emptiness in
this lifetime
okay another reason to see emptiness
directly
in this lifetime and we don't talk about
it much
and the scriptures don't talk about it
much
but but seeing emptiness directly
is a kind of
it's a kind of karma that will always
have a certain result
okay seeing emptiness directly
always triggers a certain event in your
next life
okay and what's that you meet your
teachers
young okay you meet your teachers
young when you see emptiness directly
you plant the seeds to never
again be without a direct teacher
who knows what they're talking about
from birth
from childhood you meet them age five
age six
okay it's incredible that's the idea
in the monastery of the word chuku
or tulku okay and and and that word gets
thrown around people don't know what it
means
there's arguments about whether this
guy's a took or not sometimes two guys
get to be the same toku
sometimes it's possible in the sim dooku
but the point is of the cool thing
about being a reincarnated llama
is that after you die and you get to the
bar though and you come into this life
you know
screaming and pooping you have a teacher
waiting
there for you it's so co i mean people
don't talk about it
but imagine what it's like
try to imagine what it's like you know
within
a year or two or within a few years of
being born
you have surrounding you these high
llamas
these great masters okay and that's
guaranteed
it's very similar to the
self-made buddhist karma and it's part
of the self-made buddhist car
okay anyway you are surrounded by
great teachers okay and
out of all the karmas in the universe
the karma to meet a really great teacher
is extremely rare
extremely rare so here you are you know
you're born
and they're sitting waiting for you to
be able to talk
and it's awesome i'm just saying
it's one of the cool things about seeing
emptiness
that they don't talk about much but here
they talk about it
okay it's so wonderful
to have a guarantee that after you die
and go through that sucky rebirth thing
on the other side of the fallopian tube
there's gonna be
some people waiting for you who know
what they're talking about
you know and that's so uh
to feel that to know that that's true
okay
you get you could get virus you could
die yeah i know but
what the heck i got i already got them
waiting for me
you know i'm okay i'm all right
you know yeah i could die from the virus
but those
dudes are waiting for me to pick me up
to pick up where i left off in this life
and that's one of the beautiful things
about seeing emptiness directly
is is that okay
and he mentions it here and i'm happy he
finally mentioned it okay
um
[Music]
the wisdom of a self-made buddha
springs back after rebirth basically
that's the point okay all right
uh the book he just quoted is
the middle way what's who wrote dan
who wrote the middle name it's a
nickname for
where's that then it's a nickname for
negotia's book okay sometimes i undergo
this book
is called root text on the middleway
sometimes it's called wisdom
and sometimes among people who know
it's called middleweight i just read
middleway you're like what negotiation
wisdom
okay which is the next
or the two retreats from now we're gonna
go deep into negotiations middleweight
okay
which is really
fun and confusing
all right yay uh
and you should try okay don't avoid
by the way in buddhism it's a tradition
to to study stuff
that you is hopeless in buddhism
it's a tradition to study things
that there's no way you're gonna
understand it because it pulls you up
it forces you to stretch
okay it's like your soccer coach says
you know
i used to do rowing they would say run
up and down the
stadium 20 times you know in the winter
because the ice was covering the
lake we couldn't road so they say go out
and run up and down the stadium 30
40 times you know and it was the in the
middle of winter in new jersey
you get to the top you throw up
because it's so hard and then you run
down and you run up again and you throw
up whatever's left and
and at the end in the spring that's what
happens
down at the bottom no
this terrible smell everybody in the
football scene is like what is
that smell like anyway to push yourself
spiritually is really cool okay it's
like yoga
because sometimes you just push yourself
okay
all right uh next thing
if you see emptiness directly in this
life
your next life is going to be picture
pal
nah there's a picture yeah there you go
i just love this picture it feels like
a lady uh taking her some
deep book i'm thinking of that book you
guys gave to veronica
speaking of whom uh what is that
the daily altar she treasures that like
unbelievable
and uh she she's like that all the time
she has it in her hand all the time
every morning and uh so if you see
emptiness directly in this life
in your next life you're always going to
have this book in your hand
and you're going to spend your whole
life uh
with this wisdom just surrounded by
wisdom all the time okay
so isn't that cool those are for you b
nice thing all right so
first of all there'll be people waiting
for you right
and then secondly uh the books will be
waiting for you
okay the wisdom will be waiting for you
okay
so that's another reason why i i really
encourage you to try to see emptiness
directly okay
there will be people waiting for you
as soon as you're born and there will be
wisdom waiting for you
and it's a guarantee it's it's connected
to the idea of a self-made
it's a guarantee it's impossible that it
doesn't happen
cool tim are we doing the lottery
oh okay here we go by the way that's a
good place to end it
okay so the idea of a self-made buddha
is wrapped up in the idea that you die
you come back and there are wise men and
women
waiting for you personally and they have
all this wisdom
to hand to you and share with you as
soon as you john brady's waiting there
on the other side and you and you see it
you see ahead and it's such a comfort to
know
the the babysitter's there and john
brady's there with the books
and then you're like you're like okay so
i
catch myers it's okay i i know where i'm
going
and i know who's waiting for me and i
know what's waiting for me okay
cool tim all right thank you geshe-la
so we were unable to get our lottery
winner online but we have
like their questions we're having
trouble getting these guys online yeah
uh thanks for the amazing teachings i've
had many aha moments
but there's still something going on in
my mind
how is it that buddhas actually help us
i'm trying to develop the idea of
bodhichitta in my own heart
but i'm struggling a lot because i
intellectualize everything
if i become a real bodhisattva and then
a buddha
who are all of these countless beings
that i'm helping
okay how concretely how do i teach them
and then how do i receive those
teachings from them
okay cool cool and
it's an interesting dynamic okay and
first first thing i'd like to say is
that
uh this the process of to some gum what
does it mean
learning thinking and meditating
much of it is intellectual and and it's
not a bad
thing okay it's kind of like einstein on
steroids
okay it's like the goal
is to be uh super
intelligent because then you can help
more people
super intelligent with compassion
so imagine uh einstein with
uh i don't know
christ's love in his heart or something
imagine somebody who's a combination
you know a physician
who is both technically
skilled excellent at what they do
physically dexterious to sew up your
operation and uh at the same time
ultimately compassionate i mean i'd
rather have
a compassionate being who knew how to do
the operation
you see what i mean so uh it's not a bad
thing
in fact it's the goal in buddhism
that you will become super intelligent
like
much beyond einstein and then
you will be become super
compassionate so if it seems like
you're spending a lot of time thinking
in these classes
that's a good thing and there's some
kind of
prejudice against that nowadays i don't
know in some countries or in some
communities you know you shouldn't think
too much or
or you're overthinking it in in this
tradition it's not possible
okay the more you think the better
the more you understand
the better and you can't understand if
you don't
think okay so thinking in this tradition
is highly desirable you want a surgeon
working on your heart who has thought
about how to do it
okay seriously and uh
and you want them to have love okay but
so that's the first thing to say okay
and the second part of the question was
you know what's the dynamic what happens
and this is the beauty
of the buddhist power in the diamond way
is that your karma gets so
good that all the people around you
are teaching you everybody everybody you
meet
is teaching you your karma gets so
powerful
towards the end that you never meet
anyone
who's not teaching you something
in and i keep thinking uh how we drive
back to tucson from
so diamond mountain's in the middle of
nowhere
and if you drive to the next big city
there's also nothing between here and
there like you're trying to get a good
meal
forget it you know there's one
uh shop on the highway called
the monster and uh
and for three dollars you can go in the
shop
and they'll show you the monster i never
wanted to spend the three dollars
i think you also have to swear not to
tell anybody
what he looks like if you pay your three
dollars so i don't know i never paid the
three dollars okay
uh and i'm not asking okay i don't want
to break the faith
uh but uh
the people you meet at the monster is a
is a weird thing
i have stopped at the burger king at the
monster
uh i have because i was hungry and
uh i said i'll take
they said they're advertising a veggie
burger
and i'm like you guys got veggie burgers
they're like yeah we got veggie burgers
i'll take one god i didn't know you guys
out in the middle of nowhere in cattle
country
you're selling a veggie burger and the
guy said yeah we got veggie burgers
and he he unwrapped the hamburger
and he took out the meat and he
re-wrapped it and handed to me and
charged me more than the hamburger
and so the kind of people you meet in
those places
you know who came to see the monster for
three dollars
uh you're like you know must be some
poor uneducated person right you think
that you really do think that i know
it's prejudice but you think that
and uh what i'm saying is
when you get to the end of the practice
you're gonna learn a lot from the poor
uneducated
hamburger cook at the monster
and that's how it happens that's when
you get
close to the end of your when you get
through your
diamond wave practice it should feel
like that
it should feel like you don't have to
wait to next life
that there's three sages waiting for you
to teach you
you find them in the monster burger king
and they start teaching you they start
telling you something
and you're like oh my god the buddha is
hanging out at the monster burger king
you know so yeah that is the process and
it comes from
overthinking okay
that's how you get to the monster burger
king okay